[Music]
welcome back five minute for his fans
and also all of my students that I
forced to watch these videos today's
concept of hormesis is one of my
favorite foundational fundamental
principles that I cover in basically
every class because it explains so many
issues related to exercise that app
tation aging nutrition supplementation
etc once you understand how this works
you need to under you can apply it to
any concept you're interested in and
that helps clear up a lot of confusion
when you're trying to figure out what's
good what's bad to take the to etc I
also see people miss apply this concept
a lot and tricky with marketing so what
you're seeing back here is a basic curve
okay and hormesis really means is at
some dose something might be toxic for
example but another dose it won't be so
a very basic understanding would be say
a particular drug at this level is not
toxic but if you give it to me at this
level that becomes toxic okay
now applied to something like water for
example okay here you go on our
horizontal axis this could be something
like health and on our vertical axis is
amount so if I if you are completely
dehydrated right we all know that your
health would be poor or your performance
whatever metric you want here if I give
you a little bit more water or a little
bit of water you start getting better if
I continue to give you more water you
would get better and better and better
performance in the well but if you're
already you hydrated or normally
hydrated and I gave you more water you
may actually see discomfort reduction in
performance for health fact if I
continue to give you that you might get
into what's called hyponatremia I don't
if I continue to give even more you may
actually die so that in theory even
something like water has a toxicity
curve where complete lack of it could be
deadly but also two months of it would
be deadly we call that drowning right we
could apply this to anything else
vitamins minerals now vitamins are a
little bit easier especially the water
soluble ones like vitamin C you'll
probably just pee it out but things like
minerals iron for example you got to
really pay attention to this so if you
have an athlete who is here with their
iron saturation and you just say irons
good for you accuse you red blood cells
etc ticket
and it actually pushes them in this
direction especially men you could be
having real problems you could actually
be harming their performance and in
theory you could actually eventually be
lethal
right now it's pretty hard to do that
with again vitamins especially because
you probably start throwing off get sick
first but it could start reducing
performance it could also influence
other minerals and vitamins and those
are gonna have a help heavy and/or huge
influence on your hormone levels so may
not be quite as dramatic as death but
you could start feeling really bad and
performing poorly fiber is another one
of my favorite examples I would
encourage you to check out my crucio
stuff he's done a lot of great things in
this area but here's a good example
right so if you're too low in fiber
you're constipated but if I give you too
much well you know what happens right
now in a separate video I will talk
about the pros and cons of high and low
fiber situations cuz I do them
intentionally with my athletes sometimes
I intentionally bring them too low of
fiber sometimes too high depending what
we're doing but this is really something
that's it's really important understand
we can do the same thing with oxygen
right none of you want to be completely
void of oxygen but I forgive you all the
oxygen in the world you would actually
die immediately it's how we treat
chemotherapy right it's super toxic
replacement
so that's hormesis the take-home message
here is whenever you're going to
recommend sub especially things that
come in to concentration or dosages that
are non natural pharmaceuticals drugs
mineral supplements things like that be
really careful about prescribing someone
something if you don't know where
they're at on this curve because even
something that you think is a hundred
percent good for you like water or
oxygen there are no free passes
nothing is always good are always bad
for you if you're right there the same
thing that would make you feel amazing
would make you feel terrible if you're
right there and that friends and family
is hormesis
you
[Music]